[
  {
    "id": 1,
    "question": "In all discussions on Indian knowledge system in this unit, three terms are closely intertwined. They are",
    "options": [
      "darshana, gyan, and vidya",
      "gyan, swarup, atman",
      "brahman, gyan, parlok",
      "prabhu, aatma, dristhi"
    ],
    "answer": "darshana, gyan, and vidya"
  },
  {
    "id": 2,
    "question": "The entire body of knowledge is divided into two sets in Mundak upanishad. They are:",
    "options": [
      "Aapara and param",
      "Parth and para",
      "Para and apara",
      "para and empara"
    ],
    "answer": "Para and apara"
  },
  {
    "id": 3,
    "question": "\"In the context of an oral culture, knowledge is predominantly stored in the mind rather than external media\" the mentioned statement about Indian knowledge system is",
    "options": [
      "Incorrect",
      "Correct",
      "Irrelevant",
      "not mentioned anywhere"
    ],
    "answer": "Correct"
  },
  {
    "id": 4,
    "question": "The four-point reference system allows:",
    "options": [
      "the identification of statements down to the unspecific sutra and ekarika, facilitating recall and transmission.",
      "the identification of statements down to the specific sutra (aphorism) and karika (verse), facilitating accurate recall and transmission.",
      "the identification of statements down to the specific episutra and karika (verse), facilitating accurate recall and transmission.",
      "the identification of statements down to the specific sutra and karika, not facilitating recall."
    ],
    "answer": "the identification of statements down to the specific sūtra (aphorism) and kārika (verse), facilitating accurate recall and transmission."
  },
  {
    "id": 5,
    "question": "\"Pramanas are the tools or instruments through which knowledge is acquired, validated, and understood \"this statement is",
    "options": [
      "True",
      "False"
    ],
    "answer": "True"
  },
  {
    "id": 6,
    "question": "Logical and rational inquiry",
    "options": [
      "emphasizes the use of analysis, and critical thinking only",
      "emphasizes the use of reason, analysis only",
      "emphasizes the misuse of reason, analysis, and critical thinking to understand and validate knowledge.",
      "emphasizes the use of reason, analysis, and critical thinking to understand and validate knowledge."
    ],
    "answer": "emphasizes the use of reason, analysis, and critical thinking to understand and validate knowledge."
  },
  {
    "id": 7,
    "question": "Interconnected aspect of the Vaisesika ontology include,",
    "options": [
      "Attributes and action",
      "Action and reaction",
      "Deeds and karma",
      "Karma and action"
    ],
    "answer": "Attributes and action"
  },
  {
    "id": 8,
    "question": "Pramana refers to: 1. \"pramana\" refers to the means or sources of valid knowledge... 2. These pramanas serve as epistemological tools...",
    "options": [
      "1 only",
      "2 only",
      "1 and 2 both",
      "none"
    ],
    "answer": "1 and 2 both"
  },
  {
    "id": 9,
    "question": "Samasya Refers to: 1. Samsaya\" refers to doubt or uncertainty... 2. Samsaya represents a state of mental confusion...",
    "options": [
      "1 and 2",
      "1 only",
      "2 only",
      "none"
    ],
    "answer": "1 and 2"
  },
  {
    "id": 10,
    "question": "The Nyäya school of philosophy focuses on:",
    "options": [
      "Logic only",
      "logic and epistemology",
      "epistemology only",
      "none of them"
    ],
    "answer": "Logic only"
  }
]